<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Phillipes Venus Wherein is pleasantly discoursed sundrye fine and wittie arguments, in a senode of gods and goddesses, assembled for the expelling of wanton Venus, fro m among their sacred societie. Enterlaced with many merrye and delightfull questions, and wittie answers: wherein gentlemen may finde matter to purge melanchollye, and pleasant varietie to contente fancye.</title>
            <author>M., Io.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06687</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17143</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106972</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842677</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842677</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7354</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06687)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7354)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 477:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Phillipes Venus Wherein is pleasantly discoursed sundrye fine and wittie arguments, in a senode of gods and goddesses, assembled for the expelling of wanton Venus, fro m among their sacred societie. Enterlaced with many merrye and delightfull questions, and wittie answers: wherein gentlemen may finde matter to purge melanchollye, and pleasant varietie to contente fancye.</title>
                  <author>M., Io.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by E. Allde] for John Perrin, and are to be solde in Paules Church yard at the signe of the Angell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Io. M.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7354:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7354:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Phillippes Venus. Wherin is pleaſantly diſcourſed ſundrye fine and wittie Arguments, in a ſenode of Gods and Goddeſſes, aſſembled for the expelling of wanton <hi>Venus,</hi> from among their ſacred ſocietie.</p>
            <p>Enterlaced with many merrye and delightfull Queſtions, and wittie anſwers: Wherin Gentlemen may finde matter to purge melanchollye, and pleaſant varietie to content fancye.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> ¶ Printed for <hi>John Perrin,</hi> and are to be ſolde in Paules Church yard at the ſigne of the Angell. 1591.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7354:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7354:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the Worſhipfull Maiſter Henry Prannell, <hi>I. M. wisheth health and proſperitie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Oorſhipfull Sir, it hath been</hi> an olde and ancient adadge, and that <hi>vbi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> in generalitie confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, namely, that good will may be blamed by ſome curious car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, that with <hi>Gorgon</hi> belch forth their venome againſt the ſimple, but to excuſe ſuch as meane well, Hope to beate downe feare and to ouerthrowe diſpaire, ſetteth in her foote, to animate the vertuous to perſeuer and goe forward in their well dooinges, confirming the old approued prouerb, with this aſſertion, (though trueth may be blamed ſaith ſhe, yet ſhall good will in trueth be neuer aſhamed: thus in this cauſe Hope is an inſtrueme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſent from the heauens, ſtoppeth the mouths of monſtrous <hi>Momus,</hi> oppreſſeth the outrage of <hi>Zoilus,</hi> and giueth to the honeſt and good minded, a corſſelet of proofe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter againſt the ceaſeles ſcandalls of the wicked: This hope of your good liking, hath made me bold to acquaint and deliuer into your hands this ſmall pamphlet, namely, <hi>Phillippes <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus,</hi> but to preſent <hi>Apollo</hi> with <hi>Pans</hi> Oaten Pipe, or <hi>Diana</hi> with a Diſtaffe, it were a thing ridiculous, but hope pleadeth good will, and ſaith your wiſdome wil franckly condiſcend to couer the defectes, that through mine vnskilfulnes ſhall heerein be coutched. <hi>Sinates</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered the <hi>Perſian</hi> King <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> a handfull of faire water, which his ſoueraigne thankfully receiued, I in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his gift, come vnto you with a gift far inferiour,
<pb facs="tcp:7354:3"/>
and yet I aſſure you my good wil ſtriueth to counteruaile his curteſie, but had I the precious pearles of <hi>Patroclus,</hi> or the golden Sandes of <hi>Ganges:</hi> I could finde in my hart to make you the owner of them, as wel as I haue choſen you to be the patron of my trauaile, vnder whoſe buckler of defence I haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted my Book to the printers preſſe, but becauſe I will obſerue decorum, and auoide teadiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, this ſinode and ſolemne parliament holden of the Gods and Goddeſſes in ſacred <hi>Olympus,</hi> ſhall reueale a plain and ſimple method, the occaſion and effect of <hi>Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus,</hi> the which as time and leaſure, ſetting aſide your ſearious affaires, ſhall permit you, I am fullye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded you will throughly peruſe and reade: that doon, I truſt you will giue your cenſure in ſuch ſorte, that heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after I may be incouraged to publiſh ſome other treatiſe, which may further delight you. Thus leauing you to the mercifull and gratious protection of the almighty, I bid you moſt hartily farwell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your woorships to commaund</hi> Io. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:7354:3"/>
            <head>¶ Phillippes <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ithin the high and aunti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Olympus,</hi>
               </hi> high by reaſon of his vertue, and auntient for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie: was there holden a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall and princelike Parliament, by the ſacred Synode of all the Gods and Goddeſſes. The cauſe of their ſitting, was by reaſon of a great ſlaunder raiſed through the outragious fullyes of that vaine and wanton <hi>Venus,</hi> whom by a common conſent for her ficklenes, was baniſhed the compaſſe, circuit, and ſcope of the ſtately and orient Heauens.</p>
            <p>She exiled, the Senate was quieted, contentions allayed, and all things well pacified: but as there is no counterfaite without his blemiſh, no bloſſome but hath her blaſt, nor flower without his branne: ſo to that commoditie, was added this diſcommoditie: that her ſeate being now voide of a ſoueraigne, her place of a Princes, and garde of a Goddeſſe: cauſed <hi>Cupid</hi> to care, <hi>Mars</hi> to mourne, but <hi>Vulcan</hi> to ſmile: rumours ranne throughout the Senate, and priuie mutterings heard, in euery Seſſion dayly billes were exhibited by the Amorous, and the Louer pleaded for his Ladye as he would haue doon for his life: there might you haue ſéene the ſadde lookes of the Ladies, the heauye counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of many a carped Knight, and like <hi>Aeſops</hi> frogs ſo importunate for a Quéene, that had not <hi>Iupiter</hi> béen in a merry mood, twenty to one it had made him ſtarke madde.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7354:4"/>At the laſt, (for what will not inuocations intreat, and dayly praiers obtaine) it was decréed by the whole houſe, that an election ſhould be made to ſupplye the want of a Godde, and ſatiſfie the petitions of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and thus it was.</p>
            <p>THere was among the ſéemely train, attending the Goddeſſe <hi>Diana,</hi> a Nymph of ſuch paſſing beautye and ſinguler vertue, that I may doubt whither to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend in her the exterior ſhape of the body, or interiour habite of the minde: her ſad countenance or ſage coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelles: her modeſty, geſtures, or merry glauncings, the ſharpenes of her wit, without wantonnes or ſwéetnes of her ſpeech, without wilfulnes, the attire of her bodie was comely, yet not too coſtly: her ornaments all ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet nothing ſuperfluous: for the moſt parte ſo ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, that ſhe excelled all other of her ſer, in all things ſo rare, that ſhe ſeemed rather a Saint, then a ſubiect: and to write without partialitie, who euer behelde her, would rather iudge her a mate for the greateſt God in heauen, then a companion for the mightieſt Monarche on earth: more like <hi>Phoebus</hi> Siſter, then her ſeruant: and better beſeeming a Goddeſſe, then the hand-maide of a Goddeſſe.</p>
            <p>This Dame was by birth royall, in behauiour cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, bearing a ſhape importing her owne name <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> the modeſty of her Miſtreſſe <hi>Dyan, pallas</hi> wit, and <hi>Iunoes</hi> maieſtie, <hi>Lucretias</hi> faith, with <hi>Artimeſias</hi> loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: In ſtature not of the talleſt, but indifferent in all proportions, nothing meane but abſolute and excellent: ſo that ſhould I note with my pen the halfe of her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, I ſhould therin erre with my pen, and ſinne in péeuiſhnes.</p>
            <p>This ſéemely Saint or rather gallant Goddeſſe (for what was it her beautye might not promiſe? and her
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:7354:4"/>
vertues performe? my <hi>Venus</hi> attending the entraunce of the Capital, the interuent and comming of her Lady Miſtreſſe, was not ſo happie as wiſhed for, eſpied of the mightye <hi>Iupiter,</hi> who beholding her bountye, but admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her beauty: ſo farre excelling the reſt her fellowe Nimphes in brauerie, as the Sunne in brightnes excée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth <hi>phoebae,</hi> or <hi>phoebae</hi> in bignes the little <hi>Boetes,</hi> wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vp and downe as halfe in a mamering deuiſing ſome ſtrange ſhape to entertaine his rare Miſtreſſe.</p>
            <p>Now adioyning to the entrance of the Capital, was there an outward chamber curiouſly hung with a ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Arras, wrought with golde and richlye beſet with Turkaſſes, Saphires and Diamonds, as beſt beſeemed the maieſtie of ſo braue a place, and the preſence of ſo heauenlye perſons: héere before they entred the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall, which was richlye emboſt with roofes of beaten gold, and pillarde with Iet, round wrought and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with Emeralds and Criſocolles, did the Gods make their firſte obuent, and decke them with robes wherin they ſat the day before in the Senate.</p>
            <p>In this place ſat all the waiting Nimphes, atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the comming of their Ladye Goddeſſes: and as that time fell out, miſtruſting the houſe would fit lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then their accuſtomed manner: deſputed how to driue the day in ſome merry method, wherin euery one paſt her cenſure, till <hi>Venus</hi> in the midſt gaue after this manner her ſentence.</p>
            <p>Ladies (quoth ſhe) and my fellowe Nimphes, to make a long proceſſe to little purpoſe, or to vſe many woords to little woorth, were but to pull <hi>Hercules</hi> ſhooe on a Childes foot: to burne one Candle, in ſeeking ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: to exerciſe our tungs, fill our eares, but deceiue our expectations: to talke of warre, were too vnſéeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye for women of Science, not fitting our ſexe: what then? Loue, that in trueth beſt is beſéeming Ladies,
<pb facs="tcp:7354:5"/>
and ſithence we all ſtudie which way to paſſe the time, let vs all conclude to vſe ſome merry paſtime: whereto all agreeed, and liked ſo well of the motion, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further ſpéeche, they made vp the match, and ſaide it ſhould be loue: Their order was thus, ſhe that cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly and moſt comely could courte little <hi>Ganymede,</hi> ſhould be miſtreſſe of her fellowes, and Ladye of Loue for that yéere: and by whome ſhould the triall be, but by the Boyes troth, that being tyed to his fancy, might all reſt vnder his fauour, and whom <hi>Ganymede</hi> ſaid I loue, to her ſhould fall the lot.</p>
            <p>Now was the Boy at the nether end of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, whither it were knitting of true loues knots in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes to try his wits, or making or Puppits to paſſe the time I wot not: but <hi>Venus</hi> ſkipping lightlye from her ſeate, ran haſtily to the childe, and catching him in her armes, kiſſing the prittie wagge, placed him with the women.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ganymede</hi> whither geſſing ſhrewdly at the matter, or groping ſubtilly (as the wanton well could) at wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens mindes: why <hi>Venus</hi> ſaide he, will you rauiſh me before all this companye, or rifle me amid this crue? it becommeth not Nimphes of <hi>Dians</hi> train, to entermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with Pages of <hi>Iupiters</hi> troupe: fire and water agrée neuer in one veſſell, it is dangerous to caſt flax to fire, Apples to Children, liberty to Louers, were it not for the place <hi>Venus,</hi> I would hardly like your practiſe: Coy elfe (quoth <hi>Venus</hi>) are you ſo collerick? no <hi>Venus,</hi> (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Ganymede</hi>) take héed you wax not frantick, for women ſpeake not vntill they be ſpurred, but put once out of their meane, then are they paſt all mean, becauſe you ſhould not fall into a miſchéefe by reaſon of idlenes: I did but whet your wits <hi>Venus,</hi> to finde you exerciſed, for this age is wicked, ſubiect to many euilles, and the houſe ſitteth long, and I wiſt not how you would ſpend
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:7354:5"/>
the daye: to courte <hi>Ganymede,</hi> ſaide <hi>Cyane,</hi> and why ſo? replyed <hi>Ganymede,</hi> to whet your minde or my man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: bothe anſwered <hi>Venus,</hi> for by our controuerſie ſhall <hi>Ganimede</hi> finde our conceite, and by thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall we know <hi>Ganimedes</hi> wit: if that be all La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies (ſaide he) begin when you will, <hi>Ganimede</hi> is with you and for you. Haue with you then quoth <hi>Cyane,</hi> and <hi>Ganimede</hi> let this exordium be for you.</p>
            <p>Where the late adultreſſe <hi>Venus</hi> was wrapt with deſire of her faire <hi>Adonys,</hi> no bird neſtled her breſt but beautie: when in pride of her dietie, ſhe graced <hi>Phao</hi> with an extraordinary fauour: what was the greateſt gift but beauty? and what <hi>Venus</hi> I wot not ſtriuing in thy nature <hi>Ganymede</hi> to excell her Art, hath more then naturally inriched thée with a hue of greater (if greater may be) then excelling beautye: if <hi>Venus</hi> were with her owne woorkes taken, no meruaile then if <hi>Cyane</hi> be with ſo excéeding a power ouer-taken: I loue <hi>Gani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mede,</hi> ſweete <hi>Ganimede</hi> I loue, I loue thée, yea thée, a fairer then whome, is not contained in compaſſe of our Sphere, or of greater beautye, no one reſteth heere in <hi>Olympus:</hi> if the Gods for a fauour of their inferiours to enrich them with any bleſſing of liberalitie, graunt them loue: if our Ladye miſtreſſe in fauour to their Gods, haue no greater graunt then loue: if loue made the King of our Capitall become little <hi>Cupids</hi> captiue, driue <hi>Iuno</hi> to ielouſie: and <hi>Cynthia</hi> though ſhe ſéeme ſurely to ſmile ſometime on her welbeloued <hi>Endymion:</hi> but if <hi>Ganimede</hi> in my diſputation grauiled, make any doubt of my deuice: <hi>Mars, Neptune,</hi> yea <hi>Pluto</hi> and wiſe <hi>Apollo</hi> himſelfe, ſhall ſatiſfie him in loues perfections and praiſes.</p>
            <p>Thus I loue <hi>Ganimede,</hi> yea <hi>Ganimede</hi> I loue, then let not <hi>Ganimede</hi> repaye for loue, hate: but carying
<pb facs="tcp:7354:6"/>
beautye in his forhead, harbour <hi>Excomeſis</hi> loue in his hart: for beauty long ſince and loue were both conioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in an endleſſe league of amitie: if beautifull, then is <hi>Ganymede</hi> louelye: and therefore louelye becauſe beautifull, ah witles <hi>Cyane,</hi> what ambiguitie doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thou in <hi>Ganymedes</hi> loue, that ſhineth ſo orient in pride of his beautye, but admit beautye were not <hi>Cyane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea marye, ſaide <hi>Ganymede,</hi> héer I ioyne with <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ane,</hi> for admit no beautie in <hi>Ganymede:</hi> yet anſwered <hi>Venus</hi> (ſtanding by) bereaue not <hi>Cyane</hi> of her beautye <hi>Ganymede,</hi> for it is her life: nor of life <hi>Dorye</hi> another Nymph ſtanding by, leaſt you looſe her loue: I admit them (concluded) <hi>Ganymede,</hi> both <hi>Cyans</hi> beautye and life: becauſe ſhe ſhall not perriſh in her loue, all this is but a pauſe ſaide <hi>Venus,</hi> to bring <hi>Cyane</hi> to her pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: yet hardly anſwered <hi>Cyane</hi> ſhal I procéede, if you thus penne me from my purpoſe: howbeit to make vp her medlye, forward ſhe goeth in this manner.</p>
            <p>Let not the modeſty of thy yeeres ſweet <hi>Ganymede,</hi> fruſtrate the defart of my praiſes, but lengthen my life with thy beauty, thou wilt grace my beauty with thy loue: vnfitting were it, faire <hi>Iupiters</hi> Page ſhould now become foule ingratitudes Priſoner: I tell thée <hi>Gany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mede,</hi> to forget iniuries is not the meaneſt poynte of wiſdome: to rewarde defart, the higheſt type of a true <hi>Trophea,</hi> whither was <hi>Alexander</hi> more famed for his victories of the worlde, or infamous for the ſlaughter of his faithfull <hi>Clytus?</hi> ingratitude I tell <hi>Ganymede</hi> hath fruſtrated mightye Princes of the loue of their people, hath decayed Kingdomes, and ruinated the weale of the happieſt worlde: if any <hi>Ganymede</hi> coulde but diſcearn what difference there were in remundica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a ſweete deſert, and practiſe of a ſcorning deſire:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7354:6"/>
what deſtinction betwéene a pleaſant replye, and a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing repulſe: greater ſhould be his ſweetnes exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in theſe vertues, then others vertues practiſing no ſuch ſwéete.</p>
            <p>He that hath read the Trophies of the Romain tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphes, ſhall there finde in a Princely breaſt, a prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like bountye: who for the purchaſe of eaſe, repaies with rewarde of life: perfourming a regall office in a Lyons nature: well may he be tearmed a King, that Kinglye dealeth with his vaſſailes: ſhewing that in greateſt perſonages, ought to harbour greateſt vertues. Swéet mouſe, in this let me intreate thée reſemble <hi>Aeſops</hi> mouſe, that as he with his teeth releaſed the Lyons thrauldome, thou with thy tung vntye thy Goddeſſe bondage: eaſe her thoughts, whoſe hart fainteth with the burden of thy beautye; and make thy ſoueraigntie rather pleaſing by thy liberality, then indurate through thy tirannie: ſo ſhalt thou be honoured with thy infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, praiſed by thine equalles, and loued of thy ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours: carrye with thy Lyons lookes a Lyons minde: who being King ouer my thoughts, become princelike in thy deedes.</p>
            <p>And is there among mortall wights a thing of more immortall reſemblaunce then loue? deuine are his cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which worketh deuine effects, and a matter without compare for forme, whoſe incomparable forme ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſo rare a matter: were <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> heere to deuine his <hi>principio,</hi> or <hi>Plato</hi> to diſtinguiſh of his cauſe: they both would recant their blinde ouer-ſight, and conſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them with me, commend my braue in-ſight: look about <hi>Ganymede,</hi> and beholde this goodlye Theatrum of the heauens, praiſe the Skyes with thoſe glorious Lampes of thine, and ouerviewe the baſe earth, and tel me if either farre or neere, aboue or belowe: there be
<pb facs="tcp:7354:7"/>
any thing of greater compare then vnitie.</p>
            <p>Séeſte thou not what a heauenlye hermonye there is of celeſtiall, reunited by great art to vpholde a great charge, where nothing is ſuperfluous, eche one ſerueth orderly the other, the Sunne imparteth her light to the Moone and Starres, the Moone and Starres with due proportion lymiting times and ſeaſons: bodies belowe gouerned by powers aboue: yea, there liueth not one perſon, but is guided by a Planet: one is croſſed with aduerſity, he hath felt the fury of angry <hi>Saturne:</hi> another liueth pleaſant, faſt bound in wedlockes ſacred bandes: who doubteth whither <hi>Iuno</hi> hath ſhewed her his fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, ſome fortunate in enterpriſes, ſome I account ſafe ſholded with the maieſtie of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> other ſome trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant in the conqueſt of their Ladies loues: then earſt our <hi>Venus</hi> flattered in her pride, and this is too manifeſt a preheminence ouer th'inferiours, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end they might honor and loue their ſuperiours.</p>
            <p>Now let not <hi>Ganymede</hi> born on the earth, but nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the heauens: loued of the Gods for his beautye, but honoured among men for his dietie, become vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, ſo goodly graced with all the ornaments of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine nature: if neither the earth that bread thée can challenge any of her right, yet let the heauens that har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor thee, receiue ſomewhat for their due: then leaſt ſtriuing to become more then a God, thou proue leſſe then a man: repugne not heauen and earth, leaſt being an enemye to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one, thou proue odious to the other and leſſe fauourable to me, ſcarſe acceptable to thy ſelfe: be not ſo ſtraite laced <hi>Ganymede</hi> in thy conceite, nor haue no ſelfe will which engendreth a ſelfe woe: carry in thy ſwéete bodie a ſwéete minde: content is greater riches then a Kingdome, and loue nothing inferiour to life: be as thou ſéemeſt, a God for beautye, and ſéeme that thou
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:7354:7"/>
oughteſt, to be more then a God for thy bountie: imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate him, whoſe commaundes makes him thy mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and be not coye to thy miſtreſſe: accept the courtinges of <hi>Iuno,</hi> the one ſhall enrich thee with great honors, the other honor thée with fortunate matches. Héer would <hi>Cyane</hi> no doubt haue continued a long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, had not <hi>Ganymede</hi> (turning to <hi>Venus</hi>) interupted her proceſſe with this parliance.</p>
            <p>Beleeue me <hi>Venus, Cyane</hi> hath laid on loade for her loue, and hardlye ſhe galleth me for ingratitude: but concearning the beauty ſhe treateth off, I neither yéeld the conceite, nor conſent: but tell me <hi>Venus,</hi> is not <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ane</hi> a merry wench? it is but her cuſtome <hi>Ganymede,</hi> and nothing ſtrange among vs Nimphes ſaide <hi>Venus,</hi> to be pleaſant.</p>
            <p>But tell me <hi>Venus</hi> (replyed <hi>Ganymede</hi>) are all Nymphes thus pleaſant? yea, anſwered <hi>Venus,</hi> al plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Nimphes, of the which number now ſtriueth <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ane</hi> to be one: and I allowe her contention, if you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it: Ladies (ſaide the Boye) then muſt <hi>Ganymede</hi> needs like it, yet will I reſerue a further ſentence, till I heare further ſaying.</p>
            <p>Héere <hi>Dorys</hi> becauſe ſhe ſaw <hi>Cyane</hi> interrupted, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in a greter muſe, burſt ſuddainly into theſe tearms of purpoſe to raiſe mirth: <hi>Ganymede</hi> (ſaide ſhe) women men ſay, are of their firſt louers paſſing coy, of their laſt paſſing curious: feare cauſing the firſt, loue the latter: whither of theſe I wiſt not, <hi>Cyane</hi> is fallen into, ſo that if you ſuſpence ſome cenſure, you depriue <hi>Cyane</hi> of her ſence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clymen</hi> another Nimphe ſtanding by, replyed vpon <hi>Dorys</hi> in this manner: not of ſence, but of conceite: ſhe hath doon ſo ſuperlatiue well, that I iudge her wrapt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſecond heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7354:8"/>
               <hi>Cyane</hi> hearing them deſcanting thus on her plaine ſong, to marre their muſick rowſed from her muſe, and with a ſtearne geſture, ſuch as women vſe when they are waſpiſh: thought to conclude her tenor in ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording tune, had not the houſe diſagreeing on certaine poyntes, ſuddainly been diſmiſſed, and they compelled by conſtrainte to attend their Lady Goddeſſes, where I muſt leaue them to their ſeruice, my ſelfe tyed to their ſecrets: whom becauſe I may not reueale, for that they belong to women, I will reſt with <hi>Phaebus,</hi> and expect <hi>Auroras</hi> glad appeare.</p>
            <p>BY this had <hi>Tytan</hi> tane his reſtie Stéedes, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them vnto his Chariot, when <hi>Mercurye</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwift winged meſſenger ſaluteth him from the King of Gods after this manner.</p>
            <p>Faire <hi>Phaebus</hi> ſaide he, from my Father <hi>Ioue</hi> I haue to gréete thée, and thus it is: he craueth thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence to ſit with him in Parliament: ſhall, ſaide <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo,</hi> then faire <hi>Terra</hi> be of her light be refte? not ſo (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Hermes</hi>) for this day the heauens as earſt with ſable cloudes ſhal ouer mantled he: ſo that thine abſence is no miſſe to men, &amp; yet as acceptable will it proue to the Gods: &amp; to auoide Dame <hi>Tellus</hi> diſtemperature, my Father will diſpoſe a plot that beſt may fit their profit.</p>
            <p>Short tale to make, it was not long before that all addreſſe and betake them to their ſollemne counſelles, whoſe decrées becauſe they egreſſe my purpoſe, they muſt exceede my pen, <hi>Qui ſupranos, nihil ad nos,</hi> Starres may be poynted at, but not pulled after: me liſt not treate of the ſecrets of Gods, being the mean of al men: nor intermeddle with the heauens, leaſt with the <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheonis</hi> I be ouerwhelmed in the earth: I had rather ſit in the Sunne with <hi>Irus,</hi> then rule the Sunne with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7354:8"/>
               <hi>Phaeton:</hi> créepe on the earth with the Ant, then ſoare in the heauens with <hi>Icarus:</hi> I leaue the Capitall too high for my capacitie, and returne to the great Chamber where are ſitting my merry companye, whome maye I ſmoothely bring to this daies end. I ſhall performe ſuch a taſke as will glad me for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dorys</hi> and <hi>Clymen</hi> haue gotten them to a corner of the Chamber, as it ſhould ſeeme to talke of their late nightes reſt, or early mornings riſing: <hi>Venus</hi> alone in a bay windowe was buſie beholding the faire fruites of <hi>Flora,</hi> who in great brauerie adorned a garden plot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiue in the Chamber lights: <hi>Cyane</hi> no ſooner entred the preſence, but ſhe began to deſcant on the former daies parliance, and with the very ſight of the place re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued her old paſſions: <hi>Ganymede</hi> (his Lord yong <hi>Ops,</hi> now newly entred the Capitall, becauſe he would not ſit expecting the aduent of his adherents) had no ſooner recouered the Chamber, but pryed for his companions, who that day were to holde the chat: and ſoothelye to ſay, had not <hi>Ganymede</hi> driuen <hi>Cyane</hi> from her dumps, verye mellenchollye of minde had brought her to her death: which ſadde comfort when <hi>Ganymede</hi> had well viewed, he fell immediatly like a prittie wagge into his olde vaine of wantonnes: running in all the haſte to <hi>Cyane,</hi> crying arme, arme, arme: <hi>Cyane</hi> halfe amaſed, ſkipt ſoddainly from her ſeate, and <hi>Clymen</hi> with <hi>Dorys</hi> brake off their ſilent whiſpering, when <hi>Venus</hi> at his woords began to turne from the windowe, ſéeking the author of this ſodain alarme, who eſpying <hi>Ganymede</hi> encompaſſed with the companye, with her ſiluer voice refoundeth theſe woordes, the meſſengers of her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipte.</p>
            <p>In faith (Sir wagg) come you ſo ſuddainlye crying for armes? no doubt by that all haue ſaid, you wil ſhame
<pb facs="tcp:7354:9"/>
your arte: be it with ſhame or honor <hi>Venus</hi> ſaith he, I will bring it all to end: <hi>Nyphe, Hyale,</hi> and <hi>Ramys,</hi> with all the reſt of the Nymphes, being at the neather end of the Chamber, and beholding them conuocated in a clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, not vnlike their former daies order-muſed much of the match, and drewe ſomething néer to vnderſtand the matter, the which by diuers circumſtances hauing ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered ſitting eche by her fellow, expecting what would be the greeting: whoſe preſence <hi>Ganymede</hi> beholding, fearing euery one to caſt in her verdict, which in his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion ſéemed verye vaine, began with this caueat to giue them all the canuas.</p>
            <p>Ladyes ſaide he, I being héere elected as iudge, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudge on paine of my diſpleaſure, no one Nymphe open her lippes to ſpeake among this preſence, except <hi>Dorys, Cyane, Clymen,</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> wherewith euerye Ladye repaſt her laughter, demaunding <hi>Ganymede</hi> to whom he would graunt his leaue: to <hi>Dorys</hi> anſwered <hi>Gany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mede,</hi> wherefore ſpeake <hi>Dorys</hi> be it but to winne the praiſe. <hi>Dorys</hi> looking <hi>Ganymede</hi> ſteadye in the face, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding his countenance and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt of her crue, between earneſt and ieſt, ſhot foorth her bolte in this or the like bente.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cyane</hi> in her yeſterdaies courtinges, grounded her gratious loue <hi>Ganymede</hi> on thy lookes, meaſuring thy bounty, by thy beautye: but of a contrarye cenſure frame I my fancye by thy fame: preferring thy witte before anye other woorthineſſe, my reaſons in a woord are theſe.</p>
            <p>The chaſte <hi>Penelope</hi> choſe not the great Lord of <hi>Ithica</hi> for his wealth, but his wiſdome: nor <hi>Androma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, Hector</hi> for his valure, but his vertue: ſo tooke <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedia, Lentulus:</hi> and <hi>Hypperſtria</hi> wedded the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher <hi>Crates,</hi> infinite were examples, ſhould I dwell in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7354:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
their repetition, being extant in wit, and tryed by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience: I wil not héere enter in the diſcourſe of wit, but leaue you to ſuppoſe it greater then it is by coniecture, then finde it leſſe then it ought to be by triall: but this haue I heard diuers men ſay, being my ſelfe but a woman, that wit bewitcheth, when wealth wearyeth: Inuention and diſpoſition Rethoritians tell me, are two diuers things by their diuers rules, not ſo hard is the inuention in getting, as the diſpoſition in kéeping when it is gotten: Kingdomes are eaſier conquered, then kept: and Lordſhips ſooner purchaſed then loue: one thing is caſt away in a moment, that was not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in a moneth: <hi>Troye</hi> was but a day burning, that was tenne yéeres conquering: the fooliſh fiſherman that let the Eéele ſlippe through his hand into the water, was not ſo glad of his taking vp, as ſorrowfull for his ſlyding downe: the giftes of fortune are tranſitorie, ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to no time: the giftes of nature permanent, during in all times.</p>
            <p>I account it héere no fault my <hi>Ganymede</hi> to be beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, but a commendation to be wittie: nor ſcorne I him that hath wealth, but honor him that is wiſe: wit wil get wealth, but wealth ſhal neuer purchaſe wit: and yet both wit and wealth agrée in the braueſt ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye: counſell maketh the meaneſt comelye, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes ſildome or neuer counſelleth: and yet comelynes where is good counſel, is a grace that giueth the braueſt grace. I remember a Gentleman in my time mouing an Italian queſtion to an Engliſh Louer, referred him in his choiſe to the election of thrée changelings: the firſt a faire foole, the ſecond a wiſe wanton, the third a crooked Saint: becauſe of euery one he hath diſcuſſed ſo well, I ſhame to ſay any thing except I could do better. <hi>Hyperchyon</hi> neuer ſtrained his voice after he heard <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus</hi> play on his Harp: the Black-birde repreſſeth her
<pb facs="tcp:7354:10"/>
notes where the Nightingale ſound out her layes: I could héere recite to <hi>Ganymede,</hi> the commodities and pleaſures reaped by the profit of wit, were not the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition néedleſſe, being already known, and the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge manifeſt, taught by daylye experience: what at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempteth not wit? what cauſeth not wit? what offereth not wit? which diſcouereth the eminence of euils, and is a ſoueraigne medicine to recure their maladies, tryeth the ſecrets of Ladies thoughtes, and entreth conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror into their daintieſt hartes. <hi>Agamemnon</hi> had a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grace, but <hi>Paris</hi> a courtely geſture: <hi>Aiax</hi> fought hard for <hi>Achilles</hi> honors, but <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> pleaded better that got away his armour: why preferred <hi>Cornelia</hi> a poore Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler before a wealthye Mizer: and <hi>Cyrca</hi> a bell to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunt many millions of men to diſpell her enchaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſhewing her ſelfe too much like a woman.</p>
            <p>Shall I tell <hi>Ganymede</hi> what the famous <hi>Epyrote <hi>Pyrrhus</hi>
               </hi> could doo with his wit, and eloquence of <hi>Blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> entituled <hi>Roma Triumphanta,</hi> doo not deceiue me, who ſaith, that this <hi>Pirrhus</hi> was ſo eloquent and wiſe, that the man with whome once he had ſpoken, remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſo much his, that from that time forward in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence he tooke his parte, and declared his life in preſence: the ſaide <hi>Blundus</hi> alſo ſaith, and <hi>Tytus Lyuius</hi> affirmeth the ſame: that as the Romaines were of all things pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided (ſeeing he was of ſo rare wit and eloquence) for him were they ſo prouided, that no Romaine Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour conferred in his preſence, but by the mediation of a third perſon, otherwiſe he would ſo allure them with his ſweet woords, that they returned perfourming mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of little woorth.</p>
            <p>And there-vpon I conclude that <hi>Ganymede</hi> being wittie, muſt be beloued of Ladies by conſtraint, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured of duetye: So now <hi>Cyane</hi> affectes <hi>Ganymede</hi> for his beautie, <hi>Dorys</hi> for his wit thy countenance ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7354:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
a breache <hi>(Ganymede)</hi> into <hi>Cyanes</hi> breſt, thy wit woorking wonders in <hi>Dorys</hi> thoughts, if therefore <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymede</hi> be beloued for his beauty, ſhall he be hated for his wit? if for his outward ſhadowe, why not then for his outward vertue? for by that time beautye hath caſt her Cardes with indifferencye, ſhe ſhall want many an ace of wit.</p>
            <p>Héere <hi>Dorys</hi> very earneſt to haue procéeded to her purpoſe, was interrupted by <hi>Clymen,</hi> with this merrye proceſſe. Your wit <hi>Dorys</hi> is ſo good, that if we make you not to pauſe, you will make vs pant: what, what now <hi>Dorys?</hi> wit whither wilt thou? <hi>Ganymede</hi> to giue <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ns</hi> clauſe a cloſe with this verdue, caſt in his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit: <hi>Dorys</hi> ſaide he in wit, is a Doctor, who to proue me for wit ſinguler, giueth vs occaſion to thinke <hi>Dorys</hi> for wit paſt compare: I would I were <hi>Dorys,</hi> ſo wiſe to finde womens wyles, or my owne weaknes: then tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning no further then led by reaſon, I néed not for want of iudgement incurre ſuch Ladies rage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Venus</hi> perceiuing <hi>Cyane</hi> all this time ſo mute, who earſt was euer wont to be merry, thought by ſome prit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie deceit, to haue driuen her from her penſiue conceit, between mirth and game vttering this gloſe: while you treate of wit, others talke of warre: you are amid your mirth, but <hi>Cyane</hi> mornes with melancholye: truſt me the Ladye either féedes on pilles, or on diſpleaſure, her taſte ſeemeth ſo vntoothſome: why how now <hi>Cyane?</hi> I pray you Lady what chéere?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cyane</hi> was ſtung with <hi>Venus</hi> tale, and though at firſte ſhe began to ſtand, yet bethinking her ſelfe better, ſhe recouered her ſtrength, &amp; becauſe none ſhould know where the ſhowe wrong, but ſhe that wore it, with this prittie gloſe plaied on her game: I haue fed <hi>Venus</hi> (ſaid ſhe) too rife on <hi>Dorys</hi> reaſons, ſo ſweet is her fruite as if
<pb facs="tcp:7354:11"/>
ſhe bore foorth Figges: Héereat <hi>Dorys</hi> thought to catch <hi>Cyane</hi> at the nyck, requiting her curteſie with this prit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie quippe: <hi>Cyane</hi> (anſwered ſhe) euer caryeth a ſweete tooth in her head, and a ſwéet thought in her hart, beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty bréedes no other, loue as much.</p>
            <p>Héere <hi>Iupiter</hi> hauing béen ſomething earneſt in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain cauſes diſcuſſed in the Capatal, ſodainly roſe from his ſeate, forſaking the Senate: the reſt he commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to tarrye, becauſe he would haue further triall, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alone to haue a ſight of his loue: ſoftly therfore diſcended he the Capitall; and vnawares ſtealeth down on the merry knot ſitting in the great chamber, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the little Senate of pettie Nimphes and Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſels, bit the lippe in conceite, but by your leaue chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged countenance: for ſuch was <hi>Venus</hi> preſence, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies moued <hi>Ioues</hi> patience: yet becauſe his changing ſhould be perceiued of none, he entred a with-drawing Chamber by, not perceiued of any, calling in all the haſt to <hi>Ganymede:</hi> and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt of the Nymphes being earneſt in their diſcourſings, gaue little attendance to <hi>Iupiters</hi> intercourſe, ſo that he paſſed by them into the chamber before he was ſeene or heard of any, but when the Boy had once heard the voice of his Lord, it was no time to wil him hye ore the lappes of his Ladyes, but as if <hi>Aeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> droue him with the blaſt of his breath: ſo lightly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke he his company and his bench.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iupiter</hi> his page no ſooner entred his preſence, but began in theſe tearmes to ſalute his pettie perſon. Sir wagge (ſaid he) you are amidde the women when you ſhould attend my will, beholding others braueries, but neglecting my buſineſſe: I beſeeche you Sir, what Nymph was ſhe that attended your right hand while I paſſed by the left.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ganymede</hi> remembring it was <hi>Venus,</hi> and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinglye,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7354:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
infourmed his Lord, reporting her to be an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendant on <hi>Dyctymia. Venus</hi> (anſwered <hi>Iupiter</hi>) haue we been two daies ſéeking <hi>Venus</hi> in the Capitall, you hauing ſtolne her out to ſporte with you in the great Chamber? I thought (ſaide he) her ſome rare perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage being adorned with ſo rare perfections. Hye you therefore to the Senate, and tell the Gods (for this day) I adiorne the Seſſion: <hi>Ganymede</hi> as was his Lordinges meſſage, haſted him to the Capitall to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his maiſters minde: vpon the hearing wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, all the houſe roſe ſéeking no further reaſon.</p>
            <p>By this the <hi>Debyan</hi> God had diſcharged his fierye courſes, betaking him to the bower of his beloued <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> it was no time for Nymphes to chat of loue, when their Miſtreſſe to ſtop their mouthes, had abridged the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their leiſure: they moreouer poore ſoules ſo weary of their late nightes ouer-watching, are ſo drowned in ſléepe, that there is not one waking: and for my parte I ſo greatlye tender a womans eaſe, that rather then I would wake them, I will refuſe mine arte: a ſwéete ſmyling kiſſe of a Ladyes ſléepye lippe, I account farre greater treaſure then a largis at a mighty Emperours hand: reſt you therfore (ſweete loues) ſecure, voide of troubled thoughts, while I trouble others to coniecture of your ſugred mindes.</p>
            <p>NOw was it time when <hi>Cynthia</hi> forſaking her ſiluer <hi>Orbe,</hi> had left the whole <hi>Zoane</hi> vnto <hi>Apollos</hi> charge giuing leaue to <hi>Zephirus</hi> to prouide for <hi>Aeolus</hi> paſſage: the Nymphes now riſen attend their Ladyes call, and haſten forwards for their miſtreſſe quick diſpatch: ſhort tale to make, each entred the Capitall, earneſtly expect the comming of their King: I will héer repeat the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents hapned with mighty <hi>Iupiter,</hi> if any can entreate
<pb facs="tcp:7354:12"/>
               <hi>Ganymede,</hi> I dare warrant my life he ſhal hear of much prittie ſporte: the boye and his Lord long ere this are ſuppoſed loſt, and Gods graunt it my fortune to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce them happie found.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saturnus</hi> ſoon after diuers ſportings with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Paphlogo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> youth his Page, now mindeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Senate, and is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred the preſence: whether no ſooner come, but narowly he pryeth to haue a ſight of his new ſweet hart <hi>Venus:</hi> what néed I héere to note <hi>Iupiters</hi> loue, wherin none are ignorant, acquainted with his life, his cloſe courtings, glorious glaunces, and prittie practiſes: I rather leaue them to others, whoſe ſtudies haue made them famyli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar with his factions, then vndertake the charge too chargeable for my fortunes: his trewanting from <hi>Olim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> when more méeter he had béene in the heauens: and metamorphoſes of ſhapes, becauſe he would not be knowen on earth: all theſe are better deſcryed by the prying of <hi>Iuno,</hi> then the penning of a nouice ſuch as I, whoſe eares haue neuer yet made me priuie of ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, nor whoſe experience euer attained ſuch pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uities: but thus ſuppoſe, that if euer he loued any, he loued <hi>Venus,</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> more then any: if euer he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red any he deſired <hi>Venus,</hi> and my <hi>Venus</hi> deſired he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any: if euer he metamorphoſed himſelfe for any, he metamorphoſed himſelfe for <hi>Venus,</hi> &amp; for <hi>Venus</hi> was he more ſtrangely metamorphoſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for any: if he fained him ſelf <hi>Aethra</hi> to obtain <hi>Caliſto,</hi> now ſought he a more maidenly ſhape the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Aethraes</hi> to be conuerſant with my <hi>Venus:</hi> if in habite of <hi>Dyane</hi> he deceiued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Nymph <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacris,</hi> what ſhape ſought he the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> think you to deceiue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>Phaebe</hi> her ſelfe? he entertained not ſo many golden Actions, when he begat the famous <hi>Porſey,</hi> as he did the golden thougts at the view of his excéeding <hi>Venus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I dare not holde him long thus doting on his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7354:12"/>
leaſt wanting in the Senate, I encurre the hatred of the Gods and exerciſing <hi>Pentheyes</hi> contempt: I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure <hi>Pentheyes</hi> puniſhment. He paſſeth on now to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament expected of his Péeres, and my crue are now cluſtred entending their purpoſe: <hi>Ganymede</hi> haſteth <hi>Venus</hi> to vndertake her promiſed charge, and giueth charge to the Ladyes none interrupt <hi>Venus</hi> heſte. And now being ſilent, the royall crue of <hi>Carthage,</hi> the <hi>Ilyan</hi> ſtranger gréeteth <hi>Dydo</hi> after this ſemblaunce.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lycurgus</hi> (ſaide <hi>Venus</hi>) the <hi>Lacidimonians</hi> lawe gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, had neuer liued renowned in <hi>Greece,</hi> had not his lawes obſerued, maintained the ſtate of <hi>Greece,</hi> and him ſelf in <hi>Greece</hi> framed his life correſponde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to his lawes, the lawe maker muſt be no Law breaker: and he that gouerneth others, is then more wiſe, when rightlye he ordereth himſelfe: infamous is that bird, that peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the law of nature (as ſaith the olde adage) defileth her owne neſt: what <hi>Pallamides</hi> had driuen <hi>Vliſſes</hi> from <hi>Greece,</hi> had not <hi>Tellemacus</hi> care reuealed his Fathers curſſe: and what <hi>Ganymede</hi> compelled <hi>Venus</hi> to diſplay her imbecilities, had not <hi>Venus</hi> own ſentence pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced her repented follies. Pardon me Ladies and <hi>Gany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mede</hi> excuſe thy <hi>Venus,</hi> vnwilling though I am to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe vnacquainted actions: the Painter feathereth not the Shafte, ne the Fletcher handleth not the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell: who ſetteth the Aſſe to the Hare, or the Puttocke to the Partridge: The ſtock of Grapegraftors tell me, ſuteth not with the ſyence of the Medlar: nor is the ſtalke of a Thorne naturall for the graffe of a Pippin: the Gillyflower twiſe ſet, groweth double by art, when ſimply ſowen, ſhe ſpringeth ſingle by nature: long is it or the Maſtie be taught to retriue the Partridge, or the Hound of the Kitchin, to maintaine chaſe after the Hare.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7354:13"/>I ſhall but deceiue you (ſwéet Nymphes) that expect matters of ſtrange compare from <hi>Venus,</hi> when ſtrange it is any matter at all ſhould diſtill the wits of <hi>Venus:</hi> if you would <hi>Vliſſes</hi> wit, ſerch <hi>Homers</hi> tomes: if <hi>Aene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> valiant acts, read learned <hi>Maroes <hi>Aeneads:</hi> Galen</hi> ſhall giue his goods, <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> honours, and loue who ſéekes, let him ſearche the auntient houſe of proud <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyan ſulmo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I heare theſe Ladies ſay that <hi>Venus</hi> preſcribed an edict, but wil you tye me to neceſſitie? the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is your law (Ladies) without lawe, becauſe grounded on neceſſity: yet hearken faire Nymphes, <hi>Venus</hi> ſhall not be coye without a cauſe: nor hauing cauſe, contend to be curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: if you haue vouchſafed of curteſie to vndertake <hi>Venus</hi> motions, <hi>Venus</hi> for your ſake ſhall ſtraine all her vaines, either for an appologie, or an apoſtacie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ganymede</hi> muſt be courted ſay you, and <hi>Venus</hi> ſaith <hi>Ganymede,</hi> and none other muſt court him: ſhall I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie <hi>Ganymede</hi> of his loue, or theſe Ladies of their praiſes? no, <hi>Ganymede</hi> ſhall participate of my loue, but to ſatiſfie his liſt and theſe Ladies, my reaſons be it to yeelde them their rights.</p>
            <p>Oh how well ſpake <hi>Cyane, (Ganymede)</hi> in praiſe of thy beauty, and how eloquent <hi>Dorys</hi> in commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thy wit: the firſt an argument of great force in Ladies mindes, the latter a rare ſpectacie in womens manners: both theſe ſo excellent, concluding their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, that ſhame will it be to me in ſhewing my arte.</p>
            <p>Shall I like <hi>Apelles</hi> boy ſéeking to mend the Noſe, mare the Face: or the fooliſhe Fletcher excéeding my bounds, deface the forme of my bolt: O how rude ſhall <hi>Venus</hi> reaſons ſeeme, among thoſe propoſitions of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rys</hi> and <hi>Cyane,</hi> yea <hi>Cyanes</hi> beauty (<hi>Venus</hi> will imbla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7354:13"/>
thy deformetie: and <hi>Dorys</hi> wit, diſcouer thy follies.</p>
            <p>Yet Nymphes and ſwéete <hi>Ganymede,</hi> pardon me, and regarde my neceſſitie: if <hi>Venus</hi> wantonly wander it is but for neceſſitie: if ſhe digreſſe, neceſſitie: if ſhe erre neceſſitie: whatſoeuer <hi>Venus</hi> dooth, none dooth excuſe her, and accuſe neceſſitie: but ſuch burthen plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth theſe Nymphes to oppoſe on <hi>Venus. Ganymedes</hi> beautye I both admire and loue, and cannot indéed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently praiſe it, his wit, I reuerence and adore: and cannot rightly commend it, all things in <hi>Ganymede</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celling <hi>Venus</hi> ſkill: and <hi>Venus</hi> ſkill too baſe to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take <hi>Ganymedes</hi> brauerie, vnleſſe ſome <hi>Dorys</hi> or <hi>Cyane</hi> vouchſafe him their cenſures. But <hi>Venus</hi> muſt ſpeake, and what ſpeaketh <hi>Venus</hi> (Ladies) but your prayſes? whoſe wit ſo rare in defining <hi>Ganymede,</hi> haue edified you, and eternized <hi>Ganymede.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had <hi>Bellerophon</hi> lefte labour after conqueſt of the <hi>Chymery,</hi> or left him quiet after conqueſt of the <hi>Solynye: <hi>Perſeus</hi>
               </hi> Palfreye had not béene his poyſon, ne the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing <hi>Pelagus</hi> lynes priſed ſo deare, as with the loſſe of <hi>Bellerophons</hi> life. Ah me vnhappy <hi>Venus,</hi> that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie being voide of lawe, ſhould tye me to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formaunce of a law: and ſoaring beyond my pointe, fall to my vtter perdition.</p>
            <p>If I loue <hi>Ganimede,</hi> I muſt praiſe <hi>Ganimede:</hi> if I praiſe <hi>Ganimede,</hi> then for his perfection muſt I praiſe <hi>Ganimede:</hi> perfecter may <hi>Ganymede</hi> then beautye can make him, what is then left <hi>Venus</hi> (vnhappie <hi>Venus</hi>) wherin <hi>Ganymede</hi> to praiſe thée, when <hi>Dorys</hi> and <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ane</hi> haue in all partes ſo brauelye emblazoned thy praiſes?</p>
            <p>In all things there is but good, and bad: right, and wrong: little, or great: but bethinke thée <hi>Venus. Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> as ſaide <hi>Cyane,</hi> treating <hi>de principiis,</hi> declareth
<pb facs="tcp:7354:14"/>
them thrée: and <hi>Tullye <hi>de locis deliberatinis,</hi>
               </hi> other thrée: <hi>honeſtum, vtile</hi> and <hi>poſsibile:</hi> vnder <hi>vtile <hi>(Ganimede)</hi>
               </hi> I conteyne thy beauty, <hi>honeſtum</hi> thy wit: but whither wilt thou wander <hi>Venus,</hi> for thy <hi>poſsibile? <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>
               </hi> ſaith in his <hi>Ethicks,</hi> that in all things diuiſible, there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more, ſomething leſſe, ſomething equall: more or leſſe, what can there be then beauty and wit? or of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter equalitie?</p>
            <p>But <hi>Marcus</hi> ſpeaketh of a mediocratie, and that wil he haue his vertue.</p>
            <p>Well found indéede <hi>Venus,</hi> thy vertue <hi>Ganimede</hi> beares away the bell, thy beauty either with the Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers Sunne is ſcorched, or the Winters ſtorme bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted: thy wit, age weakeneth, or ſicknes preiudiceth: thy vertue <hi>(Ganimede)</hi> neither the force of <hi>Phaebus</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching rayes can enter, nor <hi>Brumaies</hi> foggie moyſture attainte: which like the Cedars in <hi>Etla</hi> neuer rot, or the <hi>Daphnean</hi> Lawrell neuer wither: keepeth with the pure Cyuet his ſwéete fauour, and the tried Adamant, his perpetuall hardnes.</p>
            <p>What maketh men on the earth famous, in their graues glorious, in the heauens immortall? but ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. This made <hi>Caeſar</hi> a mighty Emperour on earth, honoured for a God in heauen, eternized <hi>Scipio</hi> for a Saint, and that inuinſible alſydes worthily woorſhiped vnder title of an heauenly <hi>Heroes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Glad am I <hi>Ganimede</hi> although occurrent with theſe Nimphes, I yet finde ſome argument at the leaſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing diſcrepant from theſe Nymphes wherein I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe I ſhall but auere your reaſons (Ladies) though ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe mine own wits: wit ſaide I, too meane (faire Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters) to be inſerted in your diſputations, and too baſe mettall <hi>Ganimede,</hi> to incorporate with thy deuine mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: whoſe naturall proclinitie approueth my diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7354:14"/>
vnnaturall Sophiſtrie: yet <hi>Ganymede</hi> is my loue, nothing leſſe then theſe my Siſters, though my beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be inferiour, my deſire is as great: though my wit be ſo greene, all that I can ſay is vertue the handmayden of the Gods, and ſole miſtreſſe of men: vertue <hi>(Gany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mede)</hi> which beautifieth thy beauty, and couereth thy rare wit to an abſolute wiſedome, directeth thy courſe in this life, adopting it to be a further life.</p>
            <p>What, ſhal I ſhew thée the neceſſitie héerof to th'at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the <hi>ſummum bonum</hi> of <hi>Cicero,</hi> or the abſolute pathway to the felicitie of <hi>Ariſtotle:</hi> all theſe are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter knowne by the writinges of learned men, then the aſſertions of an effeminate woman: better taught the ignorant by experience, then the learned by reading: ſo amply euery way, that I cannot with indifferency com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it any way, for if he haue knowne any thing: who can conceale this from <hi>Ganymede?</hi> if he haue read any thing, what is after viewed by <hi>Ganymede?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this I hope <hi>Ganymede</hi> conceiuing good opinion of my loue, will yéelde me for a fauour, one iotte of good lyking: and though I cannot challenge nothing by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerte, yet beſtowe one fauour of <hi>Venus</hi> of almes: which if <hi>Ganymede</hi> of fauour, and theſe Nimphes of pitie ſhal graunt: <hi>Venus,</hi> will doo homage to theſe Nimphes, and reporte <hi>Ganymede</hi> onely gratious. but,</p>
            <p>Yea but (ſaide <hi>Ganymede</hi>) and none but <hi>Venus</hi> hath hit the butte and the white: <hi>Clymen</hi> ſhall kéep her rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons cloſe.</p>
            <p>And for that cloſe (ſaid <hi>Clymen</hi>) I bequeathe <hi>Gany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mede</hi> content, thankes and praiers to <hi>Ganymede,</hi> that ſo prudent hath diſcharged the diſgrace of <hi>Clymen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No diſgrace <hi>Clymen,</hi> ſaide <hi>Ganymede,</hi> but a diſmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, knowing your ſufficiencie ſuch, as better can an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer learned arguments, and eaſier argue in greater
<pb facs="tcp:7354:15"/>
exerciſes. As for this taſk, I thinke it ſo fullye perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that attend theſe Nymphes my ſentence: onelye <hi>Venus</hi> caries away my cenſures.</p>
            <p>If any thing in this my iudgement more then rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or leſſe then wit, diſpleaſe theſe pleaſing Goddeſſes: I flye no farther for fauour then the lymits of your fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes, whoſe vrgent opportunitie, haue offred this tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe opportunitie: but ſithence you haue annexed to my loue a lotte: making my woords oracles, and my ſaying a ſentence: I will with one lyppe you pronounce <hi>Venus</hi> my loue, ſtriuing no farther for maiſtrie, but accept her for miſteſſe: héere with ſo ſwéete conſent poſſeſſed theſe Ladyes contents, that with full voice they cryed all <hi>Venus, Venus, Venus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now rowſed horned <hi>Hamon</hi> from his Chaire of ſtate, and at the name of <hi>Venus</hi> all the Senate ſtoode, thinking the late exiled aduldreſſe had aproched mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger their deities, to exhybite her appeale: the caſter of the fearefull lightnings, ſtormes, and thundereth dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inward ſighes, and threates as if <hi>Lycaon</hi> were to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine new ſentence for his ſinne: or the earth bread his thundenboltes in reuenge of their boldenes: the very ſight amazed the Senate that ſaw him carry terrour in his browes, a ſecret ſilence paſſed through the houſe, and <hi>Ioue</hi> that ſtorming expected ſtrange newes remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth now <hi>Ganymedes</hi> exerciſe, and <hi>Venus</hi> name.</p>
            <p>Now hath <hi>Iupiter</hi> peace in his hart, mirth in his countenanre, loue in his minde: the Gods ſmyle to ſée their king ſo pleaſant, and the whole ſinode as it were ſung for ioye to beholde him ſo merrye: he beckeneth forthwith to the louely Sonne <hi>Maya,</hi> ſending him into the great Chamber with this meſſage, that <hi>Ganymede</hi> ſhould preſent him with his <hi>Venus</hi> to quiet his minde, and the others variaunce.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:7354:15"/>The Gods which yet knewe not <hi>Iupiters</hi> minde, loo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked ſtrangelye on <hi>Iupiters</hi> meſſage: but hearing <hi>Iou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> treate of a concluſion to their variance, they were all willing to welcome <hi>Ganymedes Venus:</hi> thus being ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt fixt the eyes of euery perſon: <hi>Ganymede</hi> after this manner bringeth in his preſent.</p>
            <p>Firſte entred <hi>Hermes</hi> with a ſtatelye pace, as if he manned <hi>Bryſeis</hi> to her Virgins bowers: then iſſued on the gallant <hi>Ganymede,</hi> a Lawrell wreathe within one hand, his loue faſt by the other: then all the Nymphes her fellowes within whoſe hands ſwéete Oliue palmes they beare, as if they then attend <hi>Dyana</hi> to chaſe, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king along the ſwéete <hi>Theſſalyan</hi> Playnes: or els the Muſes trauailing <hi>Hellicon,</hi> when they met the adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Thracian <hi>Fyrew.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>How might I heare depainte <hi>Venus</hi> praiſe, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the delight taken in her preſence, ſuch as haue felt the full exceſſe of ioye ſhall decide this doubt, whome I make my Iudges.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iupiter</hi> commaundes his Page to declare the order of their paſtime: and controuled their vanities, that made ſuch outcrye on <hi>Venus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ganymede</hi> deſcribeth his Lord the whole circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of their ieſting, and ſaide <hi>Venus</hi> vertue had meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a iudgement, deſiring the whole houſe if he had made a ſinne, without further pauſe to reuoke his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſentence.</p>
            <p>What ſhould I write héere the wonder of the Gods and Goddeſſes gathering by <hi>Ganymedes</hi> talk ſuch hope of <hi>Venus</hi> graces: I referre you to the ſequell, how re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding her abſolute vertues the whole houſe pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced a ſecond ſentence, redoubling <hi>Venus, Venus, V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> The ruler of the Welkin ſecretlye triumphes to ſee his purpoſe ſorte of good effect: commaunding <hi>Latona</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:7354:16"/>
his wedded Siſter t'aduaunce the Nymphe, into the exiles throne, calling for the boxe of ſacred Oyle, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he annointes the Lady Queene of loue: and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing placed the diademe on her head: giueth her three bleſſings with his holye hand, and as his fingers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed her temples, ſo his lippes at euery bleſſe vttered theſe tunes, <hi>viuat <hi>Venus,</hi> viuat <hi>Venus,</hi> viuat <hi>Venus.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now is the houſe diſmiſſed, the Parliament ended, and for I dare not meddle with the order of <hi>Venus</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalement: I wil write you ſomething of their progreſſe from the Parliament, ſuch as the ſhortnes of my wit will ſuffer, or ſlendernes of my pen permit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>TRyton</hi> with his Trumpet ſoundeth a retreit, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeding in a manner a ſollempne march: next <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curye,</hi> who on his ſhoulders bore a golden mace encha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with glorious Pearle: then <hi>Venus,</hi> my <hi>Venus</hi> on whoſe right hand did attend faire <hi>Ganymede,</hi> and loue-<hi>Cupid</hi> led her by the other, whoſe traine the chaſte <hi>Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana</hi> ſcorned not to beare: then <hi>Ioue</hi> was next with <hi>Iuno</hi> in his hand, <hi>Apollo</hi> then with <hi>Pallas</hi> arme in arme, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recynthia, Mars, Neptune, Vulcan</hi> and the reſt, in ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly order marched two and two: ſo did the Nymphes at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants on the trayne.</p>
            <p>And I that ſitting, muſed at this deuine and holye traine: and when all were gone and paſt, aroſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, and vowed euer to honor <hi>Venus.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>Deficiliaque Pulchra.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
